Fine Arts collection, Inclusive: 1903,1936,1937, 1975, 1982, undated, Bulk: undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Fine Arts collection
Inclusive: 1903,1936,1937, 1975, 1982, undated, Bulk: undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3839
McArdle, Henry Arthur; Hearne, Erwin M.; Yena, Donald M.
164 paintings
Collection contains paintings and other framed items from Texas history, Baylor University history, and other topics.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
While many artists painted works in this collection, the most well-known three artists represented in the collection are Donald Yena, Erwin M. Hearne Jr. and Henry Arthur Mcardle. Much of the information regarding the other paintings and their artists is unknown.
Erwin M. Hearne painted " Eight Great Moments in Baptist History," of which The Texas Collection owns six paintings. Hearne was a commercial artist and Baptist Layman and was a member of the First Baptist Church of Dallas, Texas. The Sunday School Board of the Southern Baptist Convention commissioned Hearne in 1963 to paint the "Eight Great Moments."
Another well known artist contained in this collection is Donald Yena who was came to Texas from Illinois. He studied at the Hunter School of Commercial Art and featured the American Southwest in many of his paintings. The Texas Collection houses six paintings done by Yena of the old Spanish missions in San Antonio, Texas.
The third major artist represented in The Texas Collection is Henry Arthur McArdle, who is known in Texas for his paintings on display in the Texas Capitol, including The Battle of San Jacinto. McArdle was born in Ireland and moved to America as an orphan where he went to the Maryland Institute of Art. He won the Peabody Award, a much sought after prize for art students, in 1860. McArdle served as an engineer, draughtsman, and cartographer for the Confederate Army in the American Civil War. He moved to Independence, Texas, in 1868 and taught art at Baylor University in the 1870s and 1880s. After Baylor moved to Waco in 1886, McArdle stayed in Independence, but by 1895 he had moved to San Antonio to be closer to family. He passed away on February 16, 1908, in San Antonio.
Scope and Content
The Fine Arts Inventory has been acquired over many years from many donors. Housed in the Inventory are items ranging from plaques to framed flags, though most of the collection consists of paintings. Some of the better-known works include Baylor and Texas associated people, places, and events, such as the series of paintings done by Edwin Hearne of Baptist events in Texas, and the series of paintings done by Donal Yena of Spanish missions at San Antonio, Texas.
Henry McArdle, noted Texas artist who did many paintings of historical Texas people and events, is well represented in this collection. Currently, The Texas Collection owns eight paintings by McArdle.
Arrangement
The Fine Arts collection was arranged in 2011 as part of an effort to ensure optimum storage and retrieval of materials for patrons. Items came from the Artifact collection and various manuscript collections, and a spreadsheet was created to track all fine arts paintings. This spreadsheet formed most of the data that is now in this finding aid.
Some materials in the Fine Arts collection have accession numbers and some do not. As available, artifact and manuscript collection accession numbers are noted in this finding aid.
Because the finding aid contains a record of each individual painting, select subject terms were assigned on the item level to ensure better local retrieval of connected resources.
The Fine Arts collection is currently arranged in three series: I. Baylor University, II. Texas, and III. General Landscapes.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3839.
Related Resources
Related references
Hazlewood, Claudia. "McArdle, Henry Arthur [Harry]." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2017 September 15.
"Henry A. McArdle." The Texas Collection, Baylor University. Accessed 2017 September 15.
Yena, Donald M. "Six Spanish missions of Texas: Painted by Donald M. Yena." Waco, Texas: The Texas Collection, Baylor University, 1971.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
McArdle, Henry Arthur, 1836-1908.
Subjects
Art -- Texas.; Painting -- Texas.; Spanish mission buildings -- Texas -- San Antonio.
- Baylor University, 1
  Administrative Information
  - People, 1
    - Herbert H. Reynolds, 1; Lallier, Victor
      Electronic Resources
      Collection Files
      Index Terms
      Subjects
      Reynolds, Herbert Hal, 1930-
      Genres
      Oil On canvas; framed 30.75 X 26.75 in.; unframed 24 X 20 in.
    - Presidents of Baylor, 2; Beverly, Ron
      Andrews, Reddin, 1848-1923.; Baines, George Washington, 1809-1883.; Brooks, Samuel Palmer, 1863-1931.; Burleson, Rufus Columbus, 1823-1901.; Cooper, Oscar H. (Oscar Henry), 1852-1932.; Crane, William Carey, 1816-1885.; Graves, Henry Lee, 1813-1881.; McCall, Abner, 1915-; Neff, Pat Morris, 1871-1952.; Reynolds, Herbert Hal, 1930-; White, W. R. (William Richardson), 1892-1977.
      Charcol Sketch; framed 35.5 X 26.5 in.; unframed 27.5 X 18.5 in.
    - General Edward Burleson 1194, 3; Unknown, Artist
      Burleson, Edward, 1798-1851.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 28.5 X 24 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Hosea Garrett 357.01, 4; Unknown, Artist
      Charcoal Photo; framed 32.5 X 26.5 in.; unframed 27 X 21 in.
    - Monroe S. Carroll 2000.03, 5; The Portrait Guild
      Watercolor; framed 28 X 24 in.; unframed 23 X 19 in.
    - Mrs. Hosea Garrett 357.02, 6; Unknown, Artist
      Charcoal Photo; framed 32.5 X 26.5 in.; unframed 27.5 X 21.5 in.
    - Henry A. McArdle 359.01, 7; McArdle, W.A.
      Biography/Profile
      Painting of Henry A. McArdle by his son W.A. McArdle.
      McArdle, Henry Arthur, 1836-1908.
      Oil on Canvas; framed na X 30 in.; unframed na X 25 in.
    - George W. Baines, Sr. 1208, 8; McArdle, Henry Arthur
      George W. Baines, former president of Baylor University, and great-grandfather of the President of the United States, became editor of Texas' first denominational newspaper, The Texas Baptist. Baines in the foreground, studies one of the copies still fresh from the hand-set press.
      Subjects (Persons)
      Baines, George Washington, 1809-1883.; McArdle, Henry Arthur, 1836-1908.
      oil on canvas; framed 37.25 X 32.25 in.; unframed 29.5 X 24.25 in.
    - Pat Neff 1173, 9; Salomon, S.
      Neff, Pat Morris, 1871-1952.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 33 X 26.5 in.; unframed 38 X 21.5 in.
    - Dr. Rufus C. Burleson 365.02, 10; Unknown, Artist
      Burleson, Rufus Columbus, 1823-1901.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 36 X 32 in.; unframed 22 X 18.5 in.
    - George Washington Carroll 474.01, 11; Unknown, Artist
      Portrait Painting; framed 39 X 33 in.; unframed 27 X 21 in.
    - Dorothy Scarborough 1175, 12; Unknown, Artist
      Scarborough, Dorothy, 1878-1935.
      Painting; framed 26 X 22 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Mrs. Fannie Rogers Harris 401.01, 13; Unknown, Artist
      painting on wood; framed 25 X 19 in.; unframed 19 X 13 in.
    - Mrs. William Carey Crane 1206, 1853; 14; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 38.5 X 32 in.; unframed 32.5 X 26 in.
    - Tom Connally 376.01, 15; Christmas, H.J.
      Oil On Canvas; framed 41.5 X 34.5 in.; unframed 33 X 27 in.
    - Judge W. H. Jenkins 1195, 16; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 47 X 38 in.; unframed 38 X 30 in.
    - President Pat M. Neff 302.965, 17; Sterba, Antonin
      Oil On Canvas; framed 47 X 41 in.; unframed 39.5 X 33 in.
    - Portrait of Myrtle Mainor Neff 302.966, 18; Unknown, Artist
      Oil On Canvas; framed 49.5 X 39.5 in.; unframed 42 X 32 in.
    - Dr. John Thomas Harrington 1643, 19; Unknown, Artist
      John Thomas Harrington, co-founder of Baylor University College of Medicine, Chairman of Baylor University Board of Trustees 1932-47.
      Harrington, John Thomas, 1858-1947.
      Oil On canvas; framed 44 X 39 in.; unframed 29.5 X 25.5 in.
    - Rufus Burleson 1204, 20; Unknown, Artist
      Oil Canvas; framed 55.5 X 48 in.; unframed 48 X 39.5 in.
    - William Carey Crane, 1853; 21; McArdle, Henry Arthur
      Crane, William Carey, 1816-1885.
      Oil On canvas; framed 55.5 X 47 in.; unframed 47.5 X 37.5 in.
    - Herbert H. Reynolds, 22; Williams, Lawrence
      Oil Pastel on Canvas; framed 30 X 26 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Georgia Jenkins Burleson 1200, 23; Unknown, Artist
      Matron of Baylor University, for whom Georgia Burleson Hall was named. Compiler and publisher (1901) of "The Life and writings of Rufus C. Burleson," in honor of her late husband. Charter Member, Columbus Avenue Baptist Church, Waco.
      Burleson, Georgia Jenkins, 1833-1924.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 27.5 X 23 in.; unframed 21 X 17 in.
    - Georgia Burleson 365.02, 24; Unknown, Artist
      Painting on Canvas; framed 36 X 31.5 in.; unframed 22.5 X 18 in.
    - Peter Baylor, 25; Unknown, Artist
      Charcoal on Canvas; framed 20.5 X 16 in.; unframed n/a X n/a in.
    - Herbert H. Reynolds, 26; Parker, R.
      Oil on canvas; framed 20 X 16 in.; unframed n/a X n/a in.
    - Mary Baylor, 27; Unknown, Artist
      Charcoal on Canvas; framed 20 X 16 in.; unframed n/a X n/a in.
    - Dr. Richard Byrd Burleson, 28; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 35.5 X 29 in.; unframed 27 X 21 in.
    - W.T. Gooch 465.01, 1957; 29; Baker, Carilyn Canon
      Oil On Canvas; framed 27.5 X 24 in.; unframed 21 X 17.5 in.
    - Reddin Andrews 445.01, 1885-1886; 30; McArdle, Henry Arthur
      Andrews, Reddin, 1848-1923.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 38 X 33 in.; unframed 29.5 X 24.5 in.
    - Guy B. Harrison 451.01, 31; Unknown, Artist
      printing of a Painting; framed 29.5 X 24.5 in.; unframed 23.5 X 19 in.
    - R.E.B Baylor, 32; Lea, Tom
      Baylor, R. E. B. (Robert Emmett Bledsoe), 1793-1873.; Lea, Tom, 1907-2001.
      Printing; framed 19.5 X 16.5 in.; unframed 13 X 10.5 in.
    - R.E.B Baylor[2] 1066, 33; Lea, Tom
      Charcoal or Pencil; framed 27 X 23 in.; unframed 17.5 X 13.5 in.
    - James Edward Harrison, 34; Unknown, Artist
      Harrison, James Edward, 1815-1875.
      Print of a Painting; framed 29.5 X 23.5 in.; unframed 23.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Dr. J.B. Tidwell, 35; Unknown, Artist
      Oil Painting; framed 29.5 X 25.5 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Portrait of Edward H. Cary, 36; Platter, Peter
      oil on canvas; framed 87.5 X 49.5 in.; unframed 77.25 X 39.5 in.
    - Portrait of Henry Lee Graves 1202, 37; McArdle, Henry Arthur
      As the first president of Baylor University (1845-1851), Henry Lee Graves expanded the curriculum, added departments of mathematics and classics, and raised money for Baylor's continued operations. He is also credited with the construction of the first solid masonry building on the campus at Independence.
      Graves, Henry Lee, 1813-1881.
    - Georgia Jenkins Burleson 1200, 38; Unknown, Artist
      oil on canvas; framed 27.25 X 23.25 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Samuel Palmer Brooks 370.01, 39; Wragg, Eleanor
      Oil on Canvas; framed 39 X 32 in.; unframed 29.5 X 24 in.
    - Portrait of Pat M. Neff, 40; Salomon, S.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 38 X 32 in.; unframed 28 X 21.5 in.
    - Dr. Kenneth Hazen Aynesworth 481.01, 1927; 41; Brewer, N.R.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 54.5 X 43 in.; unframed 43.5 X 33.5 in.
    - Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor, 42; McArdle, Henry Arthur
      Baylor, R. E. B. (Robert Emmett Bledsoe), 1793-1873.; McArdle, Henry Arthur, 1836-1908.
      Oil On Canvas; framed 36.5 X 31.5 in.; unframed 28.5 X 23.5 in.
    - Maude Brian Aynesworth 481.02, 1927; 43; Brewer, N.R.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 54.5 X 44 in.; unframed 43.5 X 33.5 in.
    - Louisa Jacqueline Reynolds Higgins Tryon, 44
    - Unidentified man, 44
    - B.A. Skipper, Jr., 45
    - B.A. Skipper, Sr., 46
    - Mrs. B.A. Skipper, Sr., 47
  - Places, 2
    - Marble Plaque of Baylor Building 1977.08.01, 1; Unknown, Artist
      Marble Plaque; framed 24 X 29 in.; unframed 20.5 X 16 in.
    - Baylor Alumni Center, 2; Unknown, Artist
      Watercolor; framed n/a X n/a in.; unframed 20 X 30 in.
    - Baylor Columns 405.01, 1948; 3; Thompson, M.L.
      Places
      Independence (Tex.).
      Oil; framed 29.5 X 23.5 in.; unframed 24 X 17.5 in.
    - Marble Plaque of Baylor Building 1977.08.01, 4; Unknown, Artist
    - Map of a General Development plan for Baylor University 367.01, 5; Rucker, Robert H.
      Landscape Architecture; framed 39 X 63.5 in.; unframed 33 X 58 in.
    - Bird's Eye View of Proposed Buildings Baylor University 367.02, 6; Easterwood, Birch D.
      Water Color; framed 34.5 X 70.5 in.; unframed 29 X 64.5 in.
    - Pat Neff Hall 379.01, 7; Unknown, Artist
      Colored Pencil Drawing; framed 26.5 X 38.5 in.; unframed 19 X 30.5 in.
    - Carroll Library 302.961, 8; Lake, Mary
      Subjects (Organizations)
      Baylor University. Carroll Library (Building).
      Painting; framed 19 X 23 in.; unframed 11 X 14.5 in.
    - Quadrangle Overhead View 487.01, 9; Unknown, Artist
      Pen and Ink Unfinished; framed 31 X 39 in.; unframed 21 X 29 in.
    - Remains of Baylor College Independence 1926, 10; Unknown, Artist
      Painted on Wood; framed 11.5 X 14.5 in.; unframed 8.5 X 11.5 in.
    - Painting of Pat Neff Hall and Columns at Independence, 11; Unknown, Artist
      Painting on Canvas; framed 20 X 16 in.; unframed n/a X n/a in.
    - Burleson Academic Complex Baylor University, 12; SuBose, Jean
      Oil Paintings; framed n/a X n/a in.; unframed 22 X 32 in.
    - Baylor Alumni Center[2], 13; Crumley, Ed
      Watercolor; framed n/a X n/a in.; unframed 22 X 31 in.
  - General, 3
    - Facsimile of the charter of Baylor University, 1; Unknown, Artist
      Copy of Printing; framed 28 X 25 in.; unframed 19.5 X 16.5 in.
    - Message to the Baylor Class of 1931, 2; Brooks, Samuel Palmer
      Printing of Speech; framed 21.5 X 17.75 in.; unframed 18.5 X 14.75 in.
    - Rufus Burleson Statue Picture 302.923, 3; Unknown, Artist
      Photo on Wood; framed 8 X 6 in.; unframed 6 X 4 in.
    - Martin Portrait Brass, 4; Unknown, Artist
      Brass Plaque; framed 9 X 12 in.; unframed n/a X n/a in.
    - Preliminary study for Portrait head for Judge R.E.B. Baylor 1191, 5; Lea, Tom
      Pencil Sketch; framed 20 X 15.5 in.; unframed 13 X 8 in.
    - Photos of members of 1922 Southwest Conference champion Baylor football team, 6; Gildersleeve, Fred R.
      Football -- Texas -- History.; Southwest Conference (U.S.)
      black and white photos mounted on cardboard; framed 33.5 X 28 in.; unframed 31 X 25.75 in.
- Texas, 2
  - People, 8
    - Cox Family member 2000.7, 1; Duivendyk, Van
      Photo; framed 24.5 X 20.5 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Shapley Prince Ross [Fall], 2; Unknown, Artist
      Oil On Canvas; framed 34.5 X 29 in.; unframed 31 X 25 in.
    - Unidentified Man, 3; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 29.5 X 25.5 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Portrait of Catherine Lattimore Spencer 1226, 4; Unknown, Artist
      First Woman Trustee of Baylor University 1926-1938. Chair, Women's Auxiliary, Central Texas Baptist Sanitarium, Waco. Leader in Columbus Avenue Baptist Church, Waco. First President, Waco YMCA.
      First president, City Federation of Missions. Member, Central Committee for Woman's Memorial Dormitory, Baylor. Member of State Executive Board, WMU.
      oil on canvas; framed 29.25 X 25.25 in.; unframed 22 X 18 in.
    - Emerson Henke 2000.05, 5; The Portrait Guild
      Watercolor; framed 28 X 24 in.; unframed 23.5 X 19 in.
    - Sol Hirschberg 361.01, 6; Unknown, Artist
      Watercolor; framed 29.5 X 25.5 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Unidentified Man 1205, 7; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 38 X 32 in.; unframed 32.5 X 26 in.
    - Elizabeth Kilpatrick 363.02, 8; Unknown, Artist
      Charcoal; framed 30 X 26 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Aaron Shannon 363.01, 9; Unknown, Artist
      Charcoal Photo; framed 30 X 26 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Lexie Dean Robertson 402.01, 10; Hafford, Debo
      Oil on canvas; framed 22 X 19.5 in.; unframed 18 X 15.5 in.
    - Neil McLennan 1171, 11; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on canvas; framed 30.5 X 21.5 in.; unframed 26.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Christina Campbell McLennan 464.01, 12; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 30.5 X 21.5 in.; unframed 26.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Albert Henry Newman 364.01, 13; Shorter, Edward S.
      Historian and professor of church history at Baylor University.
      Baylor University -- Faculty.
      Oil on Canvas; framed 32.5 X 26.5 in.; unframed 26 X 21 in.
    - Portrait of Louey Migel 360.01, 14; Unknown, Artist
      Oil Portrait; framed 30 X 26 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Matilda Haynes 362.02, 15; Unknown, Artist
      Pastel Portrait; framed 30 X 26 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Governor Richard Coke 1179, 16; Unknown, Artist
      Coke, Richard, 1829-1897.
      Oil On canvas; framed 29.5 X 25.5 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Sam Houston, 17; Buerkle, Judy
      Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.
      Oil On Canvas; framed 27.5 X 23 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Underhill Mixon Carroll 1184, 18; Unknown, Artist
      Painting; framed 39 X 32.5 in.; unframed 27.5 X 21.5 in.
    - Francis Calhoun Parker 384.01, 19; Unknown, Artist
      Francis Calhoun Parker was a niece of John C. Calhoun. The rest of this portrait was destroyed when Union soldiers burned the Parker mansion during Sherman's March to the Sea.
      Photo; framed 21.5 X 19 in.; unframed 6 X 9.5 in.
    - Judge R.E. Davenport 378.01, 20; Davenport, Laura C.
      Painting on Canvas; framed n/a X n/a in.; unframed 26 X 22 in.
    - Mr. & Mrs. Sims 382.01, 21; Unknown, Artist
      Charcoal Photos; framed 19.5 X 25.5 in.; unframed 15.5 X 21 in.
    - Aldon Lang 2000.04, 22; Unknown, Artist
      Painting on Canvas; framed 28 X 24 in.; unframed 23.5 X 19 in.
    - O.M. Roberts 1192, 23; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 36 X 29 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23 in.
    - Mrs. Francis W. Edwards Roberts 1193, 24; Unknown, Artist
      Painting; framed 36 X 29 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23 in.
    - Herbert H. Reynolds, 25; Duivendyk, Van
      Picture Painted on Canvas; framed 36 X 30 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23.5 in.
    - Woman at the Well 375.01, 26; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 52 X 34 in.; unframed 45 X 26.5 in.
    - Dr. John Thomas Harrington, 27
      John Thomas Harrington, co-founder of Baylor University College of
      Medicine, Chairman of Baylor University Board of Trustees 1932-47.
    - Porfino Diaz 352.01, 28; Romero
      Oil on Canvas; framed 61.5 X 40 in.; unframed 55 X 33 in.
    - Supreme Court Justices, 29; Unknown, Artist
      Multiple Pictures; framed 34 X 28.5 in.; unframed 27 X 21.5 in.
    - Painting of 2 Southern Girls 397.01, 30; Corley, Vi
      Painting on Canvas; framed 34.5 X 28 in.; unframed 29.5 X 23.5 in.
    - Unidentified Man 1943.7-a, 31
    - Unidentified Woman, 32; Unknown, Artist
      Oil Portrait on Canvas; framed 34.5 X 29 in.; unframed 27 X 22 in.
    - Neill and Elizabeth Simpson, 33; Hainmky
      Painting on Canvas; framed 40 X 35 in.; unframed 34.5 X 29 in.
    - William Breustedt 14 when Painting, 34; Lamb, Adrian
      Oil On Canvas; framed 25.5 X 21 in.; unframed 19.5 X 15.5 in.
    - Jefferson Davis 391.01, 35; Unknown, Artist
      Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889.
      Photo; framed 20.5 X 17 in.; unframed 12 X 10 in.
    - Robert E. Lee 391.02, 36; Unknown, Artist
      Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870.
      Photo; framed 20.5 X 17 in.; unframed 12.5 X 9 in.
    - Nannie Elizabeth Houston, 37; Unknown, Artist
      Painted on Wood; framed 31 X 28 in.; unframed 22 X 19 in.
    - Gene Autry: All American Cowboy, 38
      framed X in.; unframed X in.
    - Portrait of John Thomas Harrington, 39; Adams, Wayman
      oil on canvas; framed 35.5 X 28 in.; unframed 31 1/2" X 23 1/4" in.
    - Mrs. Shapley Prince Ross (Fall), 40; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 34.5 X 29 in.; unframed 31 X 25 in.
    - Major Isham H. Earle 374.01, 41; Unknown, Artist
      Photo; framed 29 X 26 in.; unframed 16.5 X 14 in.
    - David R. Wallace M.D 2408, 42; Unknown, Artist
      Painting on Canvas; framed 29 X 25 in.; unframed 21.5 X 17.5 in.
    - Grace Noll Crowell, 43; Crowell, Reid
      Oil on Canvas; framed 43 X 31 in.; unframed 35.5 X 23.5" in.
    - J. Frank Dobie 1188, 44; Akin, V. Coleman
      Dobie, J. Frank (James Frank), 1888-1964.
      Oil on canvas; framed 36 X 32 in.; unframed 25.5 X 21.5 in.
    - Unknown man, 45; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 38.5 X 33 in.; unframed 26.5 X 21.5 in.
    - Heninrich Weidner 354.01, 46; Unknown, Artist
      Oil on Canvas; framed 35 X 30 in.; unframed 28 X 24 in.
    - Portrait of Sophie Marie Christine Chartelle Weidner 371.01, 47; Unknown, Artist
      Oil On Canvas; framed 35 X 31 in.; unframed 28 X 24 in.
    - Portrait of Sam Houston, 48; McArdle, Henry Arthur
      oil on canvas; framed 37.5 X 32.625 in.; unframed 29.5 X 24.5 in.
    - Border Mother and Son 377.02, 49; Corley, Mrs. Viola C.
      First in a series of paintings on children who live on the United States-Mexico border. Exhibited in Del Rio in 1936, Washington D.C. in 1942, and in Cumberland, Maryland, in 1945.
      Painting on Canvas; framed 39.5 X 29.5 in.; unframed 33.5 X 22 in.
    - Unidentified African American Man 2000.08, 1936; 50; Rein, O. Richard
      Oil Painting; framed n/a X n/a in.; unframed 31 X 30.5 in.
  - Places, 9
    - Horses, Wagons through the Desert 1553, 1; Mizen, Frederic
      Painted on Canvas; framed 28 X 35 in.; unframed 21.5 X 29.5 in.
    - Photograph of Bob Nelson, Center 2006.0010, 1940; 2; Unknown, Artist
      photograph; framed 26.5 X 20.75 in.; unframed 24 X 18 in.
    - Drawing of Byar's Blacksmith Shop at Washington-on-the-Brazos 380.01, 3; Burkhardt, Chris
      Charcoal Drawing; framed 25.5 X 37.5 in.; unframed 23.5 X 35.5 in.
    - Indian Portrait on Buckskin, 4; Hisethe
      Oil on buckskin; framed 35 X 29.5 in.; unframed 45 X 39.5 in.
    - Texas Flag Presented to General John R. Baylor 356.01, 5; Unknown, Artist
      Old Texas flag presented by the ladies of San Antonio during the American Civil War to General John R. Baylor.
      Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
      Flag; framed 16 X 28.5 in.; unframed 14 X 26.5 in.
    - Texas Cotton Palace Main Building, 6; Ellis, Leila
      Oil on wood; framed 17.5 X 15.5 in.; unframed 33.5 X 31.5 in.
    - Clifton Manufacturing Company, Waco World War II Service Men Plaque, 7
    - Lover's Leap Cameron Park 351.01, 8; Unknown, Artist
      Oil On canvas; framed 57 X 34 in.; unframed 50 X 28 in.
    - World War I Veterans of Troy, Texas 366.01, 9; Unknown, Artist
      Cloth Stiching; framed 33 X 49 in.; unframed 29 X 45 in.
    - Waco Tribune Herald May 16, 1975, 10; Unknown, Artist
      Raised Newspaper Printing; framed 25 X 22 in.; unframed 18 X 15 in.
    - Harrington House, 11; Nix, J.H.D.
      Painting; framed 32 X 43.5 in.; unframed 23.5 X 35.5 in.